In this first lesson, we're
going to review some of
the elements in an embeddings-based retrieval
system, and how that fits together
in a retrieval
augmented generation loop,
together with
an LLM.
So, let's go!
So, the first thing I'd
like to show you is
the overall system diagram of
how this works in practice.
The way retrieval
augmented generation works is,
you have some user query that comes in,
and you have a
set of documents which you've
previously embedded and stored
in your retrieval system, in
this case Chroma. you
take your query, you
run your query through
the same embedding model
as you use to
embed your documents, which
generates an embedding. You
embed the query and then the
retrieval system finds the most relevant
documents according to
the embedding of that query by
finding the nearest
neighbor embeddings of
those documents.
We then return both the query
and the relevant documents to the
LLM and the
LLM synthesizes information
from the retrieved
documents to generate an answer.
Let's
show how this works in practice.
To start with we're going to pull
in some helper functions from our
utilities. This
function just basically is
a basic word wrap
function which allows us
to look at the documents in a nicely
pretty printed way. And
the example that we're gonna
use, we're gonna read
from a PDF. So we're gonna pull in.
PDF Reader. This is a really
simple Python package that
you can easily import.
It's open source. And we're
gonna read from Microsoft's 2022
annual report. And so to
do that we're going
to extract the texts from the
report using this PDF
reader application and all
we're doing here is
for every page that the
reader has we're extracting the text
from that page and we're also
stripping the whitespace characters
from those pages.
Now the other important thing
that we really need to
do is make sure that we're
not sending any empty strings.
There aren't any empty pages that we
send to our retrieval system. So
we're going to filter out those
as well and this
little loop just basically
checks to see if
there's an empty string and if there is
we don't add it to
the final list of PDF texts. And so just to
show the sort of output that
we get here, we'll print an example.
And what we'll do is print the output
of the first page of
extracted text from this PDF.
And here we are, and this is what
the PDF reader has
extracted as text from
the first page of the document.
So in our next step,
we need to chunk up these pages is
first by character and by token.
To do that, we're going to grab some
useful utilities from LangChain.
We're gonna use some LangChain
text splitters. We're gonna use
the recursive character
text splitter and
the sentence transformers
token text splitter.
It's important that we
use the sentence transformers token text
splitter, and I'll
explain why in just
a moment. But first, let's start with
the character splitter.
The character splitter allows us to
divide text recursively according to certain
divider characters.
And what that practically means is,
First,
in each presented piece of text,
the recursive character
text splitter will find the double
newlines and split
on double newlines, and then if the
chunks that got split
are still larger than
our target chunk size,
in this case 1000 characters,
it will use the
next character to split them,
then the next character,
then just a space, and finally it
will split just
on character boundaries itself.
And we've
also selected a chunk overlap of 0. This
is a hyperparameter that
you can play with
to decide what optimal
chunking looks like for you. So
let's go ahead and run these.
And we're going to output
the output of the character text
splitter. We're going
to look at the 10th text
split chunk that we get. And we're
also going to output the total
number of chunks that
the character splitter gives
us. So let's run this cell
and take a look at
the output.
So we see the 10th
chunk is all of this
text according to the character,
recursive character text splitter.
And there's 347 chunks in total from
on this annual report PDF.
So now we've split by character, but
character text splitting isn't quite
enough. And the
reason for that is because
the embedding model, which we
use called sentence
transformers, has a
limited context window width.
In fact, it uses 256 characters.
That's the maximum context window length
of our embedding model. This
is a minor pitfall. If you're not
used to working with embeddings, you may
not consider the embedding model context
window itself, but it's very, very
important because typically an embedding
model will simply
truncate any characters
or tokens that
are beyond its context window.
So to make sure that we're
actually capturing all the meaning
in each chunk when we
go to embed it, it's very
important that we also
chunk according to the
token count. And what we're doing here
is we're using the Sentence Transformer text splitter,
again with a chunk
overlap of zero, and we're using 256
tokens per
chunk, which is the context window
length of the Sentence
Transformer embedding model, and
I'll go into more
detail about that embedding model in
a little bit.
And we are essentially
taking all of the
chunks that were generated
by the character text splitter,
and we are re-splitting them using the
token text splitter. Let's put
out similar output to what we had in
the last cell and see what we observe
here.
So we see a similar chunk.
It's a little bit different to
what we got before.
Obviously, it's
fewer characters because we
have only 256 tokens. This is, again,
the 10th chunk. And
we notice that we have a couple more
chunks than we had before.
In the previous output,
we had 347 chunks.
In this output, we have 349.
So it's divided a couple of the
existing chunks into more pieces.
So we have our text chunks.
That's the first step in any retrieval
augmented generation system.
The next step is to
load the chunks that
we have into our retrieval. And
in this case, we'll be
using Chroma.
So to use Chroma,
we need to import Chroma itself.
And we're going to use the
sentence transformer embedding model,
as promised.
Now, let's talk a little bit about the
Sentence Transformer Embedding
Model and what
this actually means and what an
embedding model really
actually even is.
So the Sentence
Transformer Embedding Model
is essentially an extension of the
BERT transformer architecture.
The BERT architecture
embeds each token individually.
So here we have
the class fire instruction
token and then I like dogs.
Each token receives its
own dense vector embedding.
What a Sentence Transformer does is
allow you to embed entire sentences
or even small documents like we
have here by pooling the output
of all the token embeddings to
produce a single dense vector per
document or in our case, per chunk.
Sentence transformers are great
as an embedding model. They're
open source, all
the weights are available online, and
they're really
easy to run locally. They come
built into Chromo, and you
can learn more about
them by looking up
the sentence transformers website
or taking a look
at the linked paper. So that's why we're
using sentence transformers.
And now hopefully it
makes sense why we use the
sentence transformer tokenizer text splitter. So
what we're going to do is
we're going to create a sentence transformer embedding function.
This is for
use with Chroma.
And we're going to demonstrate, basically, what happens
when this embedding function gets
cold. So that's the
output of this.
So let's take a look.
Now, you may get this
warning about HuggingFace tokenizers.
This is a minor bug in HuggingFace.
This is nothing to worry about,
perfectly normal. And here's
the output that we get. And
you can see this is one very, very
long vector. It's a
dense vector. Every entry
in the vector has a
number associated with it. And this
is the representation of
the 10th text chunk
that we showed you
before as a dense vector. This vector
has 358 dimensions, which sounds
like a lot unless you consider
the full dimensionality
of all English
text, which is much, much higher.
So the next step is to set up Chroma.
We're going to use the
default Chroma client, which
is great if you're just
experimenting in a notebook.
And we're going to make a
new Chroma collection. And
the collection is going
to be called.
Microsoft Annual Report 2022.
And we're also going to pass
in our embedding function, which
we defined before, which
as you remember, is
the sentence transformer
embedding function. We
are going to create IDs for each of
the text chunks that we've created.
And they're just going
to be the string of the number of
their position in the
total token split texts.
And then what we're going to do
is we're going to add those
documents to our Chroma collection.
And to make sure that
everything is the way we expect,
let's just output the count after everything's
been added. And let's run this
cell.
So now that we
have everything loaded into Chroma,
So let's
connect an LLM and build a full-fledged RAG
system. We're going to
demonstrate how querying and
retrieval and LLMs all
work together.
So let's
start with a pretty simple query. I
think if you're reading
an annual financial report, one of
the top questions you have
in mind is, what was
the total revenue for
this year?
And what we're going to do is we're going
to get some results from
Chroma by querying it. And we
see here that we call
query on our collection.
We pass our query texts. And we're
asking for five results.
Chroma under the hood will use
the embedding function that you've
defined on your collection
to automatically embed the
query for you.
So you don't really have to do
anything else to call
that embedding function again.
And we're going to pull the retrieve
documents out of the results.
This zero on the
end is basically saying,
give me the results
for the zeroth query.
We only have the one query.
And what we're gonna output now
is basically the
retrieve documents themselves
and take a look.
So let's run the cell.
And we see that the
documents that we get here
are fairly relevant to our query.
What was the total revenue?
We have classified
revenue by different
product and service offerings. We're
talking about an unearned revenue, and
there's more
information in a similar vein.
So the next step is to use these
results together with an
LLM to answer our query.
We're going to use GPT for this, and
we need to just do a little bit
of setup so that we can have an
OpenAI client.
We're going to load our
OpenAI API key from
the environment so that
we can authenticate.
And we're
gonna create an OpenAI client.
This is using their new
version one API where they've
wrapped everything in this one
nice client object for us. So
running the cell, there won't be
any output here, but everything's
ready to go.
Now we're going to define a
function that allows us
to call out to the model using our
retrieved results along with
our query. We're gonna
use GPT 3.5 Turbo, which does a
reasonably good job in rag
loops and is fairly quick
and fast.
So the first thing is we're
going to pass in our
query and retrieve documents.
We're going to just join our retrieved
documents into a
single string called information, and
we're going to use the double new
line to do so. We're going to
set up some messages.
So the first thing is the system prompt.
The system prompt
essentially defines how
the model should behave in response
to your input, and here we're
saying you are a helpful expert
financial research assistant. Your
users are asking
questions about information
contained in an
annual report.
You'll be shown the user's question
and the relevant
information from in
the annual report.
Answer the user's
question using only this information.
So what this is doing,
and this is really the
core of the entire RAG loop, we're
turning GPT from a model that
remembers facts into a model that
processes information.
That's the system prompt. And
now we're going to add another piece
of the message for
our user content.
And we have here that we're
in the role of the user, and
here's the content. The content
is essentially a formatted
string that says, Here's our question,
and that's just our original
query.
Here's the information you're supposed
to use.
Here's the information.
And then we need to send
the request to the OpenAI client,
which is just using the
normal API from the client. There's
nothing special here at all. We're specifying
the model. We're sending the
messages. We're basically calling the
chat completion endpoint
on the OpenAI client, specifying a
model and
the messages we'd like to send and
getting the response back.
And then we need to
do a little bit more
just to unpack the response
from what the client returns.
So we've
defined our RAG function and now let's actually
use it. Let's put everything
together.
So here's what we're going to do.
We are going to say output is equal
to calling RAG without
query and retrieve documents.
Then we're just gonna print the word
wrap output and fire away.
There we go. The total revenue for
the year ended June 30, 2022 was
$198,270 million for Microsoft.
Microsoft are doing pretty well.
Now's a good time to take
a moment and try some
of your own queries.
So remember we specified the
query a little bit further up.
What was the total revenue?
Try some of your own and see what
the model outputs based
on the retrieved results
from the annual report. I think it's
actually really important to play with
your retrieval system to gain intuition
about what the model and the
retriever can and can't do
together before we dive
into really analyzing how
the system works. In the
next lab, we're going to talk about some
of the pitfalls and common failure
modes of using retrieval in a
retrieval augmented generation
loop.